Robin Ptacek Collection
Robin Ptacek Collection
1945-2011
Ptacek, Robin.
7 linear ft.
Collection contains research files written and compiled by Robin Ptacek as they relate to melamine and, most particularly, Melmac; bulk of the materials are advertisements, correspondences, and e-bay communications.
4158104
Biographical History
Robin Ptacek was an art historian, curator, community activist, researcher, and professor.
He earned an MA in Art History from the University of California at Santa Barbara in 1982. His thesis was titled, "Highway culture iconography in pop art and superrealism." He eventually earned a PhD from the same school, completing his dissertation, "Bisson Freres: Two pioneers of photography" in 1989. In addition to teaching at various universities throughout his life, he also served as a curator of modern art at the National Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C. After retiring from his professional career, he became involved in community activism, primarily around senior and LGBT issues.
While he had maintained an interest in modernist and pop art throughout much of his life, his interest in researching and collecting Melmac was sparked during a vacation in Palm Springs, CA. He recalled entering a nearby thrift store to escape from a downpour of rain and, upon encountering some Melmac dinnerware designed by Russel Wright, his curiosity was immediately peaked.
He intended to have his research efforts culminate in the publication of a print or online encyclopedia of Melmac products, but passed away in 2012, before the project was completed.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Robin Ptacek Collection consists of research papers written and compiled by Ptacek as they relate to melamine products and, most particularly, Melmac. Melmac was the trade name of a melamine product created by the American Cyanamid Co. (it was also the name and elementary material of the home planet of 1980s TV character "Alf"). The collection contains mostly advertisements (originals and copies), communications with other melamine and Melmac collectors, and documentation of e-bay items and transactions. The collection also contains the research files of melamine collector and researcher Derek Schwartz, whose papers were given to Ptacek by Cindy Fahnestock-Schafer.
Advertisements contains original and copied clippings from magazines and newspapers, and bidding/transaction documentation.
Binders consists of 20 binders of research files of Melmac molders, producers, lines, and products.
Correspondence subject files contains mostly research and notes by Schwartz, including photocopied journals and book excerpts, inventories, contacts, and correspondences.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is divided into the series listed above, and items have been alphabatized.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing.
has made a concerted effort over the years to ensure that its manuscript and rare books holdings complement each other. As a result, many of our manuscript collections are supported by books, pamphlets, serials and other items which are cataloged in the Rare Books Collection. Please be sure to search for these related materials.
Subject and Genre Headings
Plastics; Ptacek, Robin.; Wright, Russel, 1904-1976.; Allied Chemical Corporation.; American Cyanamid Company.; Bakelite Company.; Lenox China (Firm); Royal China Company.; Melamine.; Moldings (object components); Plastics industry and trade.; Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Research notes.; Art historians.; Collectors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gregory F. Ptacek, 2014.
Inventory
- Advertisements
  - American Cyanamid Co., 1946; 1950-1952,; 1957,; 1959,; 1962 (Oversize 1)
  - Aztec, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Beetleware, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Boonton, 1954; 1958,; 1960,; undated (Oversize 1)
  - Branchell, 1956-1957; undated (Oversize 1)
  - Brookpark, 1955; 1958,; undated (Oversize 1)
  - Fostoria, 1958; 2001 (Oversize 1)
  - Kenro, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Lenoxware, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Lifetime, 1955; 1957,; 1959,; undated (Oversize 1)
  - Melamine Council, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Monsanto, undated (Oversize 1)
  - New England Advertising catalog, 1958 (Oversize 1)
  - Oneida, 1959; 1960,; 1969 (Oversize 1)
  - Plakson, 1956; undated (Oversize 1)
  - Prolon, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Royal China, 1958; 1962-1963 (Oversize 1)
  - Sears, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Texasware, 1953-1956 (Oversize 1)
  - Top Value catalog, 1956 (Oversize 1)
  - Woodbine, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1952-1952; undated; includes advertisements that feature melamine products in the background, and catalog excerpts that include multiple brands (Oversize 1)
- Binders
  - A, 1998; 2007-2008,; 2010; includes research on ABC, airline usage of melamine, Adam's House, Allied Chemical Co., Apolloware, and Aztek (Oversize 1)
  - Ba-Bo, 1998; 2007-2008,; 2010; includes research on Bakelite, Beetleware, Bessemer, Bolta, and Boonton (Oversize 1)
  - Branchell, 1998-1999; 2007-2008,; 2010 (Oversize 2)
  - Brookpark, 1998-2000; 2007,; 2010 (Oversize 2)
  - C, 1948; 1998-1999,; 2007-2008,; 2010; includes research on Clai-Ware, Capac, Carleton (Basdonware), Carlisle (Kenro), Cathamware, Chicago Molded Products, Cody, Colorado Ware, Coldspot, CMP (Malibu Ware), Corelle, Corning Ware, Couroc (Oversize 2)
  - D-Fr, 1945; 1951,; 1954,; 1998-2000,; 2007-2008,; 2010; includes research on Daileyware, Dansk, David Douglas, John Derian, Devine Foods, Dinah Ware, Diplomat, Don Wonder Ware, DOW, Duraware, Ebonyte, Ellinger's, Endura, Envoy, Evermaid, Fiesta Flatware, Fitz and Floyd, Flintwood, Fostoria, and French Bull (Oversize 3)
  - Fu-H, 1948; 1954,; 1956,; 1997-2000,; 2007-2008,; 2010; includes research on Futura, Gaydon, Gencraft, General Tire, GET, Gothamware, General Plastics Ltd., Grant Crest, Michael Graves, Hazel Pearson Handicrafts Co., Harmony House, Heller, Hemco, Hi Snack, Hollywood, Home Dynamics, and Hunter (Oversize 3)
  - Halsey, 1998; 2008,; 2010-2011 (Oversize 3)
  - I -L, 1954; 1957,; 1998-1999,; 2004,; 2007-2008,; 2010; includes research on Ideal Plastics, Ikea, Imperial International, Imperial Ware, Irwin Willert Co, Jamboree, Jason Products Ltd., Jaydon, JC Penny, Jewel Tea, Karefree, Karoff, Kartell, Keller Charles, Kenro, Kingline, Kingsway, Kirk, Krenit, Krista Ware, Kusan, Kys-ite, Laguna, Lancaster Colony, Lenox, Lexington, Libbey, and Luauware (Oversize 3)
  - Melmac ads and brochures, 1945-1966; 1998-1999,; 2007-2008,; 2010-2011; includes digitized ads and brochures from American Cyanamid Co., Plakson, Allied Chemical, Boonton, Branchell, Brookpark, Fostoria, Kenro, WorthPoint, Oneida, Texas-ware, Prolon, Watertown Ware (Oversize 4)
  - Melmac logo pcs., 1998-1999; 2007-2008; includes research on promotional Melmac items, such as those made for Barbie, McDonald's, Pacman, and Smokey the Bear (Oversize 4)
  - Melmac research, 1998-1999; articles, print-outs, e-mails, and handwritten notes (Oversize 4)
  - N-Pl, 1998-2000; 2007-2008,; 2010; includes research on National Home Products, Nemir Industries, NFC, Nichols, Noritake, Northern Air Ware, Northern Industrial Chemical, Oneida, Peoria Plastics, Plakson, Plastics, Inc., Plastomer, and Precido (Oversize 4)
  - Prolon, 1998-1999; 2007-2008,; 2010-2011 (Oversize 5)
  - R, 1998-1999; 2007-2008,; 2010-2011; includes research on Raffiaware, Rainbow Plastics, Reed Prentice, Regaline, Reinecke, Riviera Ware, Rosti, Royal China, and Rubbermaid (Oversize 5)
  - S, 1998-1999; 2010; includes research on Sakura, Sellex, Serv-rite, SiLite, Space Age Products, Spaudling Dinnerware, Stetson, Stotter, Strawweave, StyleHouse, Styson, Syscoware (Oversize 5)
  - Texasware (PMC), 1998-1999; 2004,; 2007-2008,; 2010 (Oversize 5)
  - V-W, 1998-1999; 2010; includes research on Vacron Ware, Warwick, Watertown (Lifetime), Waverly, Westinghouse, Windsor, and Russel Wright (Oversize 5)
  - Wright, Russel, 1998-1999; 2007-2008 (Oversize 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 2010; includes notes and articles on designers, makers, materials and processes, and other categories (Oversize 6)
- Correspondence subject files
  - Allied Chemical Co., 1957; 1959-1961,; 1963,; 1965-1966,; 1990 (Oversize 6)
  - American Cyanamid Co., 1960; 1990,; undated (Oversize 6)
  - Apollo Ware, 1990 (Oversize 6)
  - Bakelite, 2002 (Oversize 6)
  - Bidding, 1998; 2001; contains e-mails about bidding on e-bay (Oversize 6)
  - Book preparation, 1990-1991; contains outline and other preparatory materials for Shultz's book project on collectible melamine dinnerware (Oversize 6)
  - Boonton, 1972; 1990; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Branchell, 1957; 1989,; 1999 (Box 1)
  - Brookpark, 1959; 1990,; undated (Box 1)
  - Contacts, 1990; list of contacts for Schultz's melamine dinnerware project (Box 1)
  - Design history, 1991; undated (Box 1)
  - Fostoria, 1959; 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Fugleman, Marv, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Good Housekeeping, 1957; several pages (including the cover page) of the Good Housekeeping Christmas issue (Box 1)
  - Inventory, 1990; 1992 (Box 1)
  - Jorgenson, Jay, 2000; photography (Box 1)
  - Kenro, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Lenoxware, 1962; 1967,; 1990 (Box 1)
  - Lines, 1955; 1957,; 1990; list of melamine product lines from North American companies and some photocopied advertisements (Box 1)
  - Lucent, 1956; 1958,; 1990 (Box 1)
  - Manitoga, 1990; map to and newsletter for Manitoga, the estate of Russel Wright (Box 1)
  - Melamine: general, 1989-1990; 1997; includes a copy of Antinque Trader weekly from Feb 1997 (Box 1)
  - NHMA, 1990; National Housewares Manufacturers Association (Box 2)
  - Oneida, 1959; 1962,; 1990 (Box 2)
  - Plastics, 1945; 1989,; 2002,; undated; includes photocopies of "The Watertown book of plastics" and a "Plastics Newsfront" (newsletter of American Cyanamid Co.) (Box 2)
  - Plastics dinnerware articles, 1955; 1989,; 1993-1994,; 1996,; undated; clippings from The New York Times, Boomer, Better Homes & Gardens, an issue of Antinque Week, and The American Design Adventure (Box 2)
  - Pricing lists, undated (Box 2)
  - Production/logistics, 1989-1992; information and correspondence about publication for Schultz's book (Box 2)
  - Prolon, 1962; 1990 (Box 2)
  - Questions, 1988-1999 (Box 2)
  - RW IdealWare, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Smithsonian, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Society of Plastics Industry, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Stern, Bill, 1990; 1999,; undated (Box 2)
  - Texasware, 1962; 1970,; 1990,; undated (Box 2)
  - Thayer, Robert, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Timelines and genealogy, 1990; 1994 (Box 2)
  - To call, 1990 (Box 2)
  - US Navy, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Watertown, 1947; photocopied clippings from House Beautiful (Box 2)
  - Westinghouse, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1947-1948; 1950-1951,; 1954,; 1956,; 1962-1964,; 1986,; 1989,; 1998,; undated; 2 folders; includes photocopied advertisements, library request forms, magazine and newspaper clippings, "The dawn of a new age: Russel Wright Melmac" (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1948; 1950,; 2005,; 2010,; undated; one binder including e-mails and research files (Oversize 6)